Oak Park, Ill. Harvard Congregational Church records, 1907-1997.
Congregational Library & Archives
Oak Park, Ill. Harvard Congregational Church records, 1907-1997.
RG5588
Congregational Library & Archives
1.14 Cubic Feet
(3 boxes)
The first meeting of the Harvard Chapel was held on January 20th, 1907, and the church was formally named the Harvard Congregational Church on February 5th, 1907. The first church building was destroyed by fire in 1916 and replaced a year later. The church joined with the United Church of Christ after the denomination's formation. In 2005, the church merged with the Family of Faith church to form the Harvard Family United Church of Christ. The church remains open today. The collection contain membership and auxiliary group records and includes trustees' records, auxiliary group records, especially from the women's group, World War II related records, Sunday school records, and photographs.
Harvard Congregational Church (Oak Park, Ill.)
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by the Illinois Conference of the United Church of Christ in December 2024; accession number 2024-46.
Custodial History
Materials in this collection were given to the Illinois Conference of the United Church of Christ at an unknown time. There is no further documentation on how the materials arrived at the Illinois Conference.
Historical Note
The story of the Harvard Congregational Church in Oak Park, Illinois, began on Thanksgiving Day, 1905, when Rev. William E. Barton found an undeveloped lot at the intersection of Harvard Street and Kenilworth Avenue and declared that "upon this rock will I build my church." In 1906, the lot was purchased by a Joint Conference Committee and the first religious service on the lot was held on June 24 of that year. Ground broke on a church building in October with William Barton breaking the first ground. The first meeting of the Harvard Chapel was held on January 20th, 1907, and the church was formally named the Harvard Congregational Church on February 5th.
Rev. O. C. Grauer was the first minister of the newly formed church. He was quickly followed by Rev. C. Arthur Jevne in October, 1907. Jevne remained pastor until 1915. He was followed by Rev. Edward J. Ridings. On December 13, 1916, the church was destroyed by a fire. Following the disaster, the church met in the Circle Masonic Temple. Construction on a new church building was begun in April 1917 and the new building was dedicated on December 9th of that year. Rev. William H. Hill became the fourth pastor of the church in 1926.
After the formation of the United Church of Christ, the Harvard Congregational Church joined the denomination. In 2005, the church merged with the Family of Faith church to form the Harvard Family United Church of Christ. The church continues to serve the Oak Park community today.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains, primarily, membership and auxiliary group records for the Harvard Congregational Church in Oak Park, Illinois. The collection includes building records, trustees' minutes, Woman's Benevolent Society records, Five Point Club records, newsletters and a "diary" related to World War II, Sunday school records, a history scrapbook, photographs and a postcard, and the church's memorial book.
Arrangement
Materials in this collection have been arranged into chronological, with contiguous materials grouped together.
Baptismal records.; Church buildings.; Church membership.; Church records and registers.; Marriage records.; Necrologies.; Scrapbooks.; Women -- Societies and clubs.; Harvard Congregational Church (Oak Park, Ill.); Oak Park (Ill.) -- Church history.
- Woman's benevolent society records, 1907 1913; 1907-1913 (Box 3, Volume 2)
- Women's benevolent society records, 1913 1919; 1913-1919 (Box 3, Volume 3)
- Photographs, 1907, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Board of trustees minutes, 1910-1916 (Box 1, Volume 1)
- Anniversary and special programs, 1912 1967; 1912-1967 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Daily light circle king's daughters records, 1913 1936; 1913-1936 (Box 3, Volume 1)
- Cornerstone time capsule contents list, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Building records, 1917 1918; 1917-1918 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Woman's benevolent society yearbooks, 1925 1965; 1925, 1952-1965 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Yearbooks, 1927 1967; 1927-1967 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Oak Park facts and figures, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Memorial book, 1935 1981; 1935-1981 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Board of trustees minutes, 1937 1938; 1937-1938 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Board of trustees minutes, 1938 1941; 1938-1941 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Woman's benevolent society poem, 1940 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Five point club records, 1942 1944; 1942-1944 (Box 2, Volume 1)
- Five point club records, 1945 1946; 1945-1946 (Box 3, Volume 5)
- Record of weddings and baptisms, 1944 1997; 1944-1997 (Box 3, Volume 4)
- Neil Hanson anniversary banquet speech, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Victory in Europe Day service program, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Victory in Europe Day and Victory over Japan Day newsletters, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Sunday school records, 1951 1958; 1951-1958 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- History scrapbook, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Woman's benevolent society records, 1955 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Woman's benevolent society records, 1956 1959; 1956-1959 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Woman's benevolent society reports, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Woman's benevolent society reports, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Woman's benevolent society records, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Woman's benevolent society records, 1961 1965; 1961-1965 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Woman's benevolent society records, 1963 1968; 1963-1968 (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Woman's benevolent society records, 1968 1971; 1968-1971 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Constitution, circa 1967 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- World War II servicemen "diary", undated (Box 2, Volume 2)
- Church building exterior postcard, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)